{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Thousands of soldiers fleeing from this country attempted to surrender to the British after World War II, but they were refused and subsequently massacred in the Bleiburg Repatriation. In this country, one ethnic group barricaded the village of Berak to disrupt a 1990 election, leading to the Log Revolution. It was led during its independence war by Franjo Tudman, also its first president. This country was led during World War II by the fascist Ustase party, and its ports on the Adriatic include Split and Rijeka. For ten points, name this former Yugoslavian republic, a country with capital Zagreb.",
      "answer": "Republic of Croatia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This character claims that “five-card stud taught me a lot about mankind.” His wife sings “This is prophetic!” after receiving a glass elephant, then interrupts a performance of The Red Detachment of Women in Act II. This operatic character claims “the eyes and ears of history caught every gesture” in “News Has a Kind Of Mystery,” an aria sung just after he stepped off the Spirit of ‘76 and was greeted by Chou En-Lai. For ten points, name this title character of a John Adams opera based on his 1972 visit to China.",
      "answer": [
        "Richard Nixon",
        "Nixon in China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Historians have long debated the meaning of this ruler’s last words, “I have made but one mistake.” When this ruler complained to his father about a urine tax, his father held up a coin to him and said “money does not stink.” This ruler put down the revolt of Terentius Maximus, who pretended to be the former emperor Nero. A monument dedicated to this ruler shows soldiers carrying off treasures like a pair of trumpets and a golden menorah. For ten points, name this Roman emperor whose namesake arch commemorates his destruction of Jerusalem.",
      "answer": "Titus Vespasianus Augustus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Squatters attempted to establish the Cimmaron Territory in a portion of this state, and a proposed state in its eastern half would have had its capital at Muskogee. This state’s Unassigned Lands were opened up to settlement with the Land Rush of 1889, and the “Neutral Strip,” or “No Man’s Land,” became this state’s western panhandle. The proposed state of Sequoyah would have succeeded the Indian Territory in, for ten points, what Great Plains state just north of Texas?",
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "question": "One hundred of these objects were initially purchased by William T. Robey, while the other 600 were destroyed. A forgery of one of these objects was found on a Broward County absentee ballot in 2006. These items have recently sold for nearly a million dollars each, despite their printed price of 24 cents, and were made in 1918 to commemorate a new air mail route. For ten points, name these rare United States stamps in which the central object was misprinted upside-down.",
      "answer": "Inverted Jenny stamps"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s attempt to get his student Robert Serber appointed to a faculty position was blocked by Raymond Birge, who remarked “One Jew in the department is enough.” Haakon Chevalier offered to pass secrets from this man to the Soviets through George Eltenton. With Max Born, this man names a simplification of molecular wave functions that assumes nuclear motion and electron motion is separable. For ten points, name this UC Berkeley physicist known for his leading role in the Manhattan Project.",
      "answer": "Julius Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "question": "This region was ruled in medieval times by the Bilung family, and the city of Meissen in this region was renowned for its porcelain. This region was once split between the Lauenburg and Wittenberg Imperial Circles, and its Wettin rulers split off Thuringia from this region. One city in this region was controversially firebombed by Allied forces during WWII. Dresden is in, for ten points, what German region whose capital is Leipzig?",
      "answer": "Saxony"
    },
    {
      "question": "Support for this initiative overwhelmingly increased after an attack on Camp Holloway. Operation Flaming Dart was an early prototype of this initiative. Wild Weasels helped support this initiative that was replicated in neighboring countries under Operations Barrell Roll and Menu. Unlike the later Operation Linebacker, this initiative did not use B-52 Stratofortresses. MiGs opposed this initiative, which sought to destroy the Ho Chi Minh trail. For ten points, name this airborne carpet-bombing campaign carried out by the U.S. against North Vietnam.",
      "answer": "Operation Rolling Thunder"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote one story about the impact of war upon Carter Druses’ family in his “A Horseman in the Sky.” This author described the death of Jerome Searing in “One of the Missing,” and he also wrote a story about a young boy caught up in the battle of Chickamauga. Another story by this author describes the attempted sabotage of Peyton Farquhar before he is hung from title structure. For ten points, name this American author of “An Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge” who disappeared in 1914 on a trip to see the Mexican Revolution.",
      "answer": "Ambrose Bierce"
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader of this modern-day nation signed the Internal Settlement with Abel Muzorewa. This modern day nation was the center of a conflict that was ended with the Lancaster House Agreement. The Bush War was fought in this nation, where Ian Smith declared separation from Britain with his Universal Declaration of Independence. Smith’s power in this nation was weakened by the ZAPU and ZANU, which were respectively led by leaders Joshua Nkomo and Robert Mugabe. For ten points, name this country once known as Rhodesia.",
      "answer": "Zimbabwe"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This document’s Article III states it is the duty of the United states “to furnish each Government named in the Preamble.” John Blaine was the only senator to vote against the ratification of this agreement, which states that the signatories are “Deeply sensible of their solemn duty to promote the — welfare of mankind.” This document’s stated goal of “uniting the civilized nations of the world in a common renunciation” was not even remotely successful, but its American — co-sponsor won the 1929 Nobel Peace Prize anyway. For ten points, name this international pact that forbade the use of war for conflict resolution, named for its American and French architects.",
        "answer": [
          "Kellogg-Briand Pact",
          "names in either order",
          "Pact of Paris",
          "General Treaty for Renunciation of War as an Instrument of National Policy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After repeated international violations of the Kellogg-Briand Pact, this man, Hoover’s Secretary of State, outlined a namesake doctrine that claimed the United States would not recognize any territorial changes made by force.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Lewis Stimson",
          "Stimson Doctrine"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country in November 2015, a cargo plane carrying oil workers to the Paloch oil fields crashed after taking off from its capital in Central Equatoria. Riek Machar now leads a People’s Liberation Movement-in-Opposition in a civil war in this country; Machar briefly served as its vice president, but was fired with the rest of this country’s cabinet in July 2013. In that civil war here, Bortown, the capital of Jonglei State, was captured in December 2013. For ten points, name this African country that established its capital at Juba in 2011.",
        "answer": "Republic of South Sudan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dukes of Milan often hired what mercenary soldiers active in early modern Italy, notable examples of which included John Hawkwood and Federico da Montefeltro?",
        "answer": [
          "condottieri or condottiero",
          "or condottiere"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One emperor of this region came to power after the signing of the Articles of Favorable Treatment. The Concordia Association was the prevalent party in this region, and it was defeated in the battle of Khalkin Gol. Unit 731, a group of doctors that experimented on humans, operated in this region. Rulers of this region were known as Kangde. It was established after a victorious campaign of the Kwantung army under Hideki Tojo, and it was located in the northern region of China. For ten points, name this puppet state that was located in present day Manchuria.",
        "answer": "Manchukuo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The only emperor of Manchukuo was this final leader of the Qing dynasty, who was forced to abdicate as a child.",
        "answer": "Emperor Puyi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this work, an option of exile to Thessaly is briefly considered. This work opens with the title character admiring his friend’s calm in the face of death but bearing the bad report that the sacred ship Paralos has arrived in port, authorizing his friend’s impending execution. This work notes that injustice in the face of injustice is inherently flawed, and so the title character’s offer is rebuffed. For ten points, name this Platonic dialogue in which a friend of Socrates unsuccessfully tries to convince him to escape prison.",
        "answer": "Crito"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Athenian executions were forbidden if the sacred ship Paralos was not at home; while Socrates awaited his execution, it was on a trip to this island, where Apollo and Artemis were legendarily born.",
        "answer": "Delos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While on the run, this man used the name Fritz Ullmann before eventually returning to his birth name. One prisoner stated this man “was capable of being so kind to the children” yet “tomorrow or in a half-hour” he would send them to the crematoria. This man combated a typhus outbreak by killing an entire barracks and then having it sterilized. In one role, this man killed numerous people with heterochromia, so that their eyes could be extracted. For ten points, name this Nazi doctor whose horrific experiments at Auschwitz earned him the nickname Angel of Death.",
        "answer": [
          "Josef Mengele",
          "Jose Mengele"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mengele attempted to prove his thoughts on superior heredity by experimenting on this type of person; those experiments included chloroform injections to the heart.",
        "answer": "identical twins"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one story set during this war, characters satirically described as “representatives of virtue” ignore the title character, even though she had a picnic basket of food with those characters. In that story, a caravan of refugees from this war accidentally wander into an inn held by the enemy, and are only let go when a prostitute sleeps with the enemy officer. “Mademoiselle Fifi,” “Boule de Suif,” [sweef] and many other works of Guy de Maupassant were set during, for ten points, what war that ended the Second French Empire?",
        "answer": "Franco-Prussian War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the end of “Boule de Suif,” Cornudet starts to whistle what song, which is contrasted with “God Save the Tsar” in the 1812 Overture?",
        "answer": "La Marseillaise"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Yellow Book laid out the plan for this construction. Lucius Clay created a committee headed by Francis Turner thatsupported the creation of this system. A precursor to this system was proposed by Lawrence C. Phipps and supported by the 1922 Pershing Map. The chief proponent of this system was influenced both by his experience in the 1919 Transcontinental Motor Convoy and the German Autobahn. For ten points, name this American national project spearheaded by President Eisenhower that overhauled American transportation.",
        "answer": "Interstate Highway System"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to advocating for the Interstate system, Dwight Eisenhower advocated against the “acquisition of unwarranted influences” by what sector of the American economic landscape?",
        "answer": "Military-Industrial complex"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man railed against those who would use governmental power to pursue personal gain in his Disquisition on Government. In a speech, this man argued that “in the present state of civilization,” the intellectual differences between the races made slavery a “positive good.” This man created the Bureau of Indian Affairs while serving as Secretary of War, and held “the Union, next to our liberty, most dear” in his opposition to the Tariff of Abominations, which he believed states should ignore. For ten points, name this advocate for nullification, the southern most of the Great Triumvirate.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Calhoun attacked the Tariff of Abominations in this anonymous-published work, which was distributed to state legislators in Columbia.",
        "answer": "South Carolina Exposition and Protest"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This entity was victorious against Grand Duke Vytautas at the battle of the Vorskla river, though it had prior lost to Lithuania at the battle of the Blue Waters. This entity symbolically disintegrated after a stand-off at the Ugra river. Members of this entity filled 9 sacks full of ears following the battle of Legnica, and its greatest triumph took place against the Hungarians at Mohi. For ten points, name this most northwestern of the Mongolian Khanates, founded by Batu Khan in the 1240s, which supposedly received its name from the color of its soldiers’ tents.",
        "answer": "Golden Horde"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A civil war broke out between the Golden Horde and this other Mongolian khanate. This Mongolian khanate was led by Hulagu and, sacked Baghdad, turning its rivers black with ink.",
        "answer": "Il-khanate"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "GOING WEST",
      "prompt": "In the westward expansion of the United States, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "trail leading to the Willamette Valley and namesake of a Pacific territory?",
          "answer": "Oregon Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "Missouri city in which that trail began?",
          "answer": "Independence"
        },
        {
          "question": "group of settlers who resulted to cannibalism after being trapped in the Sierra Nevadas in 1846?",
          "answer": "Donner party"
        },
        {
          "question": "editor of the New York Tribune who said to “go west, and grow up with the country”?",
          "answer": "Horace Greeley"
        },
        {
          "question": "religious group who followed that trail after departing from Nauvoo, Illinois?",
          "answer": "Mormons or Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints"
        },
        {
          "question": "offshoot of the aforementioned trail leading to gold-rich regions of Wyoming?",
          "answer": "Bozeman Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "industry whose workers built the aforementioned trail?",
          "answer": [
            "fur traders",
            "fur trapping"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "businessman who build a namesake Pacific city to allow trading in that industry?",
          "answer": "John Jacob Astor"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "BALTIC STATES",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Baltic states, what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "northernmost of the Baltic states and less populous than Latvia and Lithuania?",
          "answer": "Estonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "largest Baltic city and capital of Latvia?",
          "answer": "Riga"
        },
        {
          "question": "war which destroyed Lithuania as a Russian coalition took on Charles XII of Sweden?",
          "answer": "Great Northern War"
        },
        {
          "question": "large European kingdom that joined a commonwealth with Lithuania in the Union of Lublin?",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "year in which the Baltic states left the Soviet Union one year before its general dissolution?",
          "answer": "1990"
        },
        {
          "question": "national sport in which Lithuania won a bronze medal in its first Olympics after independence?",
          "answer": "basketball"
        },
        {
          "question": "pre-World War II pact between Germany and the U.S.S.R. that allowed Soviet annexation of the Baltic states?",
          "answer": "Molotov-Ribbentrop pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "13th century effort of Pope Innocent III to Christianize the Baltic states?",
          "answer": "Livonian Crusade"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "PLAGIARISM",
      "prompt": "In the history of stealing thoughts from other people, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "former Delaware senator who stole speech material from Neil Kinnock before becoming Obama’s VP.",
          "answer": "Joe Biden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kentucky Tea Party Republican who stole from Wikipedia and admitted he didn’t understand footnotes.",
          "answer": "Rand Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "city where Mike Barnicle resigned from the Globe newspaper after inventing people in his columns.",
          "answer": "Boston Globe"
        },
        {
          "question": "author of Band of Brothers, who dubiously claimed he was “not out there stealing other people’s writings.”",
          "answer": "Stephen Ambrose"
        },
        {
          "question": "magazine which employed Jonah Lehrer, who consistently re-used his own material, as discovered in a 2012 Slate investigation.",
          "answer": "The New Yorker"
        },
        {
          "question": "newspaper from which Jayson Blair was fired in 2003 for inventing stories about the Iraq War.",
          "answer": "The New York Times"
        },
        {
          "question": "political magazine that fired the author of “Hack Heaven,” Stephen Glass, in 1998, and which lost two-thirds of its editor staff in 2014 in a corporate shake-up.",
          "answer": "The New Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "historian and LBJ aide whose The Fitzgeralds and the Kennedys was withdrawn to fix the issue.",
          "answer": "Doris Kearns Goodwin"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The commission investigating this event found its roots in “un-Americanism” and “paternalism.” In claiming that this event forced the nation to “the ragged edge of anarchy,” Richard (20 pts)",
        "Olney issued injunctions against several of this event’s leaders, though it took Nelson Miles to finally end it. Grover Cleveland deemed that this event disrupted (10 pts)",
        "mail and sent in troops, angering the Governor of Illinois, John Peter Altgeld. Eugene Debs was arrested for his role in, for ten points, what 1894 strike in an Illinois company town by the American Railway Union?"
      ],
      "answer": "Pullman strike or boycott, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This film ignores the 1845 death of Elizabeth Reed by claiming that Katalin Helenski was the first woman to be executed in her state. Assistant District Attorney Martin Harrison is accused of forging evidence in this film after the death of the (20 pts)",
        "Hunyak prompts Fred Casely’s lover to re-hire her lawyer. In this film, a pair of deaths in the Hotel Cicero is detailed along with a set of homicides nicknamed (10 pts)",
        "“pop,” “six,” and “squish.” Billy Flynn sings “Give ‘em the old razzle-dazzle” to win a court case in, for ten points, what 2002 Best Picture Oscar winner, a musical film that stars Catherine Zeta-Jones and Renee Zellweger as murderesses Velma Kelly and Roxie Hart?"
      ],
      "answer": "Chicago"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After taking power in 2011, this country’s current leader reached cease-fire accords with Shan and Karen insurgents. The supposed expansion of Islam in this country is opposed by the Buddhist monk Ashin Wirathu, and by its (20 pts)",
        "969 Movement. This country is home to a rebel group called the Kachin Independence Army and a Rohingya Muslim minority. It is currently led by (10 pts)",
        "Thein Sein, and its opposition National League for Democracy is led by Aung San Suu Kyi [ang san soo chee]. For ten points, name this country that moved its capital to Naypyidaw in 2005."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of the Union of Myanmar or Burma"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Amos Gerry Beman quoted this speech by comparing the “colored race” to its most famous metaphor. This speech quotes Moses’ last speech in Deuteronomy 30:15-18 by warning that “if our hearts turn away, so that we will not obey,” that “we shall surely perish out of the good land whither we pass over this (20 pts)",
        "vast sea to possess it.” In its closing remarks, this speech exhorts its audience to “let us choose life, that we and our seed may live.” This speech was delivered on board the (10 pts)",
        "Arbella as it was sailing to Salem. For ten points, name this 1630 sermon delivered by John Winthrop, that encourages the Massachusetts Bay colonists to provide a good Christian example for the world."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "A Model of Christian Charity",
        "the City Upon a Hill speech"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This religion’s main festival once featured its founder ascending a massive artificial mountain topped by a column with a statue of Hercules on it. This religion decreed celebrations called decadi at the end of every (20 pts)",
        "ten-day week. After this religion’s main proponent insisted that there existed some sort of divinity, the National Convention passed a decree replacing the (10 pts)",
        "Cult of Reason with this religion. For ten points, name this cult that Maximilian Robespierre tried to make the official state religion of Revolutionary France."
      ],
      "answer": "Cult of the Supreme Being or Culte de l’Etre Supreme"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author fictionalized the murder of Thomas Kinnear in the historical novel Alias Grace. Amanda Payne is rescued from bloodthirsty veterans of the game Painball in a trilogy by this author that includes the novels (20 pts)",
        "Maddaddam and The Year of the Flood and begins with a work in which Extinctathon is played by Snowman. In another novel, this author of (10 pts)",
        "Oryx and Crake detailed the illicit Scrabble games played in the Republic of Gilead between the Commander and his concubine, Offred [”of Fred”]. For ten points, name this Canadian author of The Handmaid’s Tale."
      ],
      "answer": "Margaret Eleanor Atwood"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After witnessing one of these events, John Francis decided to go on a journey walking all 48 of the contiguous states by foot. In 1967, Blackburn Buccaneer aircraft sent by the Fleet Air Arm dropped bombs and fuel to limit the damage done by one of these events. A dome nicknamed a (20 pts)",
        "“sombrero” and the chemical COREXIT failed to completely stop one of these events. One of these disasters was caused by the negligence of Joseph Hazelwood, who drunkenly (10 pts)",
        "ran aground in Prince William Sound. For ten points, name these events, the biggest of which began after the Deepwater Horizon blowout in 2010."
      ],
      "answer": "oil spills"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These two countries engaged in the battle of Lund, which was instigated by the earlier Treaty of Roskilde. One war between these two countries was known as the Lennart (20 pts)",
        "Torstennson war and arose over the collecting of the Sound Dues. Wars between these two countries often contested the region of Scania. The final battle between these two countries was in 1710 at Helsingborg. During the (10 pts)",
        "Thirty Years War, the Treaty of Bromesbro was signed between these two countries by Axel Oxenstierna and Christian IV. For ten points, name these two Nordic countries separated by the Oresund strait between the North and Baltic seas."
      ],
      "answer": "Sweden and Denmark"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Though he isn’t Polish, this composer wrote a cycle of 29 motets from the Song of Solomon. As musical director of the Julian Chapel, this composer wrote a book of masses based on one by Cristobal de Morales. Johann Joseph Fux wrote a book about this composer’s style, (20 pts)",
        "Gradus Ad Parnassum. This man’s most famous piece is always sung at Papal Coronation masses and supposedly convinced Charles Borromeo that music with (10 pts)",
        "multiple melodic voices was acceptable in church. For ten points, name this composer who supposedly saved polyphonic music with his Pope Marcellus Mass."
      ],
      "answer": "Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This rival of Felix Zuloaga was arrested as part of the Plan of Tacubaya. Shortly after a key victory, the French forced this man to move his capital to San Luis Potosi. Earlier, this man was exiled from (20 pts)",
        "Oaxaca [wah-HAH-kah] to New Orleans for his opposition to Santa Anna’s insistance on continuing to fight the Americans. Ignacio Zaragoza served this leader at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Puebla, after which he was able to restore the republic. Emperor Maximilian was overthrown and replaced by, for ten points, what five-time President of Mexico during the 19th century?"
      ],
      "answer": "Benito Ju´arez Garcia"
    }
  ]
}